Okay, let's get started. Uh, today we're
going to be talking about exploration.
Uh, we're going to be starting by
talking about exploration in kind of
standard reinforcement learning
settings. Uh, actually primarily in
bandit uh, settings and then how that
might translate to robotics and large
language models. Uh and then we're
actually going to revisit some of the
metalarning topics that we talked about
on Wednesday. Uh and revisit how we
might effectively learn how to explore
in meta RL settings. Uh so what is the
exploration problem? If we apply
reinforcement learning to uh to some
problems, uh we're able to solve them
quite well. So, for example, if we uh
try to trade a reinforcement learning
agent to play Breakout, where the reward
is the score of the game, uh you get a
pretty performant uh player that's able
to get a a high score. Uh but if you
instead try to train a reinforcement
learning agent to play a game like this
one on the right which is called
Montzuma's Revenge uh it's really really
hard for reinforcement learning systems
to play. Uh now why is there this
difference? So, um, in the second game,
uh, you can get a reward, uh, if you get
a key, kind of intuitively, if you're
getting a key, that's useful, uh, for
being able to progress. Uh, opening a
door is also useful. Um, and if you, uh,
there's this kind of skull that's
rolling around and intuitively, um, we
as humans know that that's probably
something you might want to avoid. Uh,
likewise, falling off of, um, off of a
ledge might be something that you'd
avoid. But these are things that the
agent doesn't know. itself. Uh, and in
general kind of completing the game, um,
like these are kind of very sparse
discrete events and completing the game
only weekly correlates with, uh, those
rewarding events. And so it actually and
each of those individual rewarding
events are also kind of few and far
between. Uh, so for example, at the
beginning, the agent isn't getting any
reward at all. uh and it has to figure
out how to even get to the key in the
first place which requires quite a long
um sequence of events. Now, as humans,
uh we kind of know what to do because we
understand what each of these sprites in
the game mean. Um but the algorithm
really doesn't know that. Uh so if we
instead try to imagine ourselves as
reinforcement learning algorithms, uh
let's think about through that a little
bit. And we can think through that uh
with a game called Mau. Uh it's kind of
a it's like half a game, half a joke in
some ways. Um the you aren't told the
rules of the game in advance. And if you
break a rule, then you get a penalty. Uh
and you don't actually know you get a
penalty, but you don't actually know
what the rule is. And you have to
discover the rules through trial and
error. Uh and when you get a penalty,
it's not always clear why you got a
penalty. uh the the rules don't actually
necessarily make sense to you. Uh and
tasks like Montazuma's revenge are
difficult um because reinforcement
learning methods they don't know about
the rules. They know very little about
what's good and what's bad uh what they
can do, what they can't do. uh and when
tasks are become longer and longer uh
this also makes the problem even more
difficult because you have to figure out
a even longer sequence of actions that
might lead to getting reward versus
getting a penalty.
Um, and so if you think about kind of
what the reinforcement learning agent
has to do, um, reinforcement learning
agents are kind of analogous to
imagining if your goal in life was to
win 50 games of of MAU.
And you also didn't even know this in
advance. You only kind of learn this
from actually getting rewards from
winning games and getting penalties from
losing games.
That's kind of like what the the
reinforcement learning system um kind of
that's the the the difficulty that these
algorithms are faced with. It's really
really hard especially in sparse reward
scenarios.
Now um if we're to think about this
exploration problem, there's a couple
different ways of looking at it.
One way of looking at it is we want to
discover highreward strategies. Uh we
want to basically seek out rewards. um
and find uh kind of sequences of actions
that individually those actions may not
be rewarding but when we sequence them
together we're able to find rewards.
Um and another way to to view um to view
the exploration problem is deciding
whether to attempt a new behavior or
continuing um to do the best thing that
it knows so far. You're basically
deciding should I try something new or
should I do something that has been good
in the past and these are actually kind
of kind of part of a single problem
where you need to uh there's kind of
this exploitation problem which is doing
what you know um will yield the highest
reward doing kind of the things that
you've seen before that have high reward
acting according to your Q function for
example
um and this exploration problem which is
doing things that you haven't done
before in hopes of getting higher
reward. Um, and so that's kind of how we
can think about this reinforcement
learning problem where we need to
balance these two objectives if our goal
is to maximize a sum of rewards over
time.
Um, as some examples, uh, if you are in
a new city, you kind of moved somewhere
new, um, exploration would be trying new
restaurants. Uh, exploitation would be
going to your favorite restaurant or the
restaurant that you like the best.
Uh, one actually very common use of
reinforcement learning is figuring out
um like which ads to place uh and and
where. Uh, and exploitation would be
taking the ad that has been the most
successful and showing that one to the
uh to the user. Uh, and exploration
would be instead trying to pick a
different advertisement at random and uh
instead showing that advertisement to
the user.
Um or uh as a kind of a final example in
oil drilling um you don't know uh where
you're going to find um where you're
going to find oil. And so exploitation
would be taking the best location that
you've uh found before that has yielded
oil versus exploration would be drilling
at a new location.
Okay. Um
so exploration is quite hard. Um, and
if we want to design an algorithm for
exploration, we might think about what
is the best strategy for exploring and
the best way to trade off between
exploration and exploitation.
Um, and we also need to think about like
what is that? What is kind of optimality
and exploration even mean?
There's a range of uh reinforcement
learning problems uh ranging from more
simple problems where you could actually
uh analyze whether or not the strategy
is optimal or not to more complicated
problems where uh it's intractable
tractable to analyze whether or not it's
optimal and also intractable to develop
algorithms that are able to uh to do a
good job at exploration. On the simple
side, uh you start with multi-armmed
bandits. um the kind of one-step RL
problems that don't have any state. Uh
and then if you want to make that more
complicated, you add context. You add
some sort of features for each uh pos uh
for for the state that you're in. You
could then move to small MDPs to larger
MDPs. Um and uh kind of a lot of the
kind of problems that we've been talking
about in this course are large MDPs
without any known structure. And those
are the ones that um that are like the
hardest for getting good exploration
strategy and also theoretically thinking
about exploration.
So
before we talk about exploration uh in
the large problems, let's talk a little
bit about bandits for a minute um
because they provide a nice way to think
about exploration and they're actually
used uh in practice uh for a variety of
problems. And um specifically the way
that we can think about uh like like
what is a bandit? Um it's not the uh
kind of someone that runs around and and
maybe tries to steal stuff or something.
Um it's uh a form a formulation of of
reinforcement learning
where
um there the horizon is is just like one
time step for a single episode.
Uh there's no state
And
um unlike everything we've talked about
in MVP so far, uh your reward is
actually stochastic.
And so um if you kind of go back to the
examples before, you could think about
the problem of selecting a restaurant as
a bandit problem where you could for
example uh select to go to uh one
restaurant. You could select to go to a
different restaurant. You could select
to go to a different restaurant and so
forth. And depending on your experience
in previous episodes of selecting
restaurants, uh you could inform your
choice about whether you want to pick a
new restaurant where you know nothing
about the reward or go to a restaurant
that you've uh you've received high
reward for in the future. And the reward
is stochastic in the sense that uh your
experience at that restaurant uh may not
be the same every single time. Uh and so
yeah, this is kind of what a bandit
problem looks like.
Now if we want to think about uh how
good is exploration uh and how good is
our kind of reinforcement learning
algorithm
uh we want to think about
um how much reward we're getting
relative to uh if we're acting
optimally.
And uh so far we've been thinking about
sums of rewards uh often time averaged
over episodes. Uh the in bandit problems
you actually are often thinking about
actually the entire reinforcement
learning process and the optimality of
the reinforcement learning process and
the optimality of exploration followed
by exploitation. And so say that you
have um
you have taken uh capital T episodes so
far.
Then the best you could have done um is
going to be something like the uh
expected reward of taking the optimal
action
times t. Uh and this is actually in some
ways an oracle uh because
when you haven't taken any episodes at
the beginning then you sort of are
forced to take a random action because
you don't know anything about the MDP so
far. Um and so this is kind of in
retrospect what is the best thing you
could have done. Um and this is a upper
bound on the sum of rewards that you
could be getting after t.
And then if we want to think about um
like how well we've been doing, we can
think about this subtracted by the sum
of awards that we actually observed from
the actions that we've taken. Um and so
that would be something like a sum from
t = 1 to t of the action like the actual
action
that we decided to take uh in each
particular episode.
And the gap between these two uh is
going to be measuring kind of like
basically a form of optimality gap. Uh
and this expression is something that's
called regret. [snorts]
And it's measuring like basically uh how
much do we regret taking the action that
we did compared to taking the optimal
action.
Now if you were to think about regret
over time um so here actually time is
indexing over episodes because each
episode is just a single time step.
So if we think we think about kind of um
as a function of the number of episodes
uh
you regret um after taking those number
of episodes uh
if you were acting optimally uh what
like what sort of curve would you get on
this plot?
Yes, I see
I see mostly uh going straight. So if
you're acting optimally, this will be
zero. Uh and it will be zero even as you
have more and more episodes. It'll be
zero in expectation. Um there might be
some randomness. Uh and so you would get
a curve that looks like this. Um and so
this is like
sort of like optimal. Um now in practice
actually achieving this is not really
possible because at the first time step
like I mentioned you have to take a
random action. [snorts] Um
now does anyone have thoughts on what
this curve would look like if you were
just taking an episode at random?
Yeah it'll keep increasing. Yeah. So if
you were taking an episode at random um
the there will now be a gap between
these and you would be getting a higher
reward from taking the optimal action
compared to taking uh that action at
random. And uh if for example you were
always picking uh A1 and A1 is not the
best action then after one episode you
would expect to have um some kind of
nonzero regret. Uh right? Uh so you
would have a curve that looks like this.
And then if you took A1 again the next
episode, then you would then kind of
incur the same uh the same difference in
optimal rewards versus uh versus the
rewards that you took. And so then this
would increase and you would actually
get something that looks linear. And
that means that basically every time you
there's basically every at every time
step there's a fixed difference between
the optimal reward and the reward that
you took. Uh and so whenever you get
like a linear uh regret increasing
linearly that means that uh your
algorithm is not actually improving. Uh
it's not actually using the exploration
to get better rewards.
Um if instead you were
The blue markers never work that well,
but we can see uh the if instead you are
actually having an algorithm that is a
bit smarter, then you would expect to
have sublinear regret. And so you would
expect to actually not just linearly
increase your regret over time, but
actually have this curve look something
like this where it starts um it starts
looking something more like linear. And
then eventually um if you then get to
the optimal behavior after exploring
then you it flattens out to something
like this. And you could imagine that uh
this portion is like you're now in the
exploitation phase and the phase before
that is when you're exploring and
gathering information about the the
problem. Uh the question is um to make
these curves are we running the learning
process a lot of different times and
then averaging um the so for these
curves this is actually each of these
curves is just like one reinforcement
learning process uh and they I guess
they're very smooth here and in practice
they'll be a little bit noisier um the
uh optimal I guess this is kind of an
expectation and so this is um this is
going to be smooth but you might have
something where For example, um in
reality, maybe you got unlucky uh kind
of one time step and it like this kind
of went up because you were got unlucky.
Maybe at the the next time step, you
still took the optimal action but got um
but got lucky. Um and so you this will
actually have some noise in it uh in
practice. Yeah. So the question is um we
have an expectation on the first part.
We don't have an expectation here. Why
is that? Um the this is basically some
measure of like the optimal expected
reward uh after t time steps. Uh this is
actually just like the actual reward
that you observed. You could also have
an expectation over this over
reinforcement learning runs. Um and that
would be uh that would then give you
like um like as an example here if you
run this algorithm multiple times these
regret curves will actually look a
little bit different depending on how
unlucky you get. Um and then if you were
to then measure this in terms of
expectations then that would be
averaging uh over different runs of the
reinforcement learning algorithm. Yeah.
So the question is uh if we taking
random actions um why is it linear and
why is it increasing by a fixed amount?
So um this will be noisy uh if you are
taking random actions. uh the
if um I don't know say that uh
so yeah it will be noisy uh if you run
it multiple times in expectation it will
be linear uh and the if you have like a
deterministic MDP and you always select
action one uh through like a very
notsmart strategy um and and the rewards
are a bit more deterministic then you
might actually get a curve that looks
like this uh so the question is if we're
always taking A1 one, then how do we
actually know how to measure this
formula? Um, this is not actually a
formula that like uh sorry
to back up a little bit, we this is
actually not um this is like what we're
aiming to we're aiming to minimize
regret. uh and we're aiming to get
something that is able to flatten out,
but this is more of an object that's
used for analysis and not our
optimization objective because we
actually can't measure this um uh
without kind of knowledge of the of the
bandit problem or knowledge of the MDP.
If you introduce an expectation here,
then you would expect it to be
monotonic. Um if not then because the
reward is stochastic uh it um you could
have scenarios where you um say that the
the best
um the best action is like a five and
the probability
um of getting like good reward is like I
don't know like 90% of the time and 10%
of the time you get a bad reward then um
you're going to see uh like when you get
a good reward it will actually um
relative to the the expert which is
averaging over that um it will go down
but if if you write this as an
expectation for the reinforcement
learning algorithm it would be
monotonic.
Cool. Um so this is the regret formula.
um regret after doing reinforcement
learning for T episodes. Expected reward
of the best action, basically the best
we can hope for and expectation uh if we
had kind of knowledge of what the of
what the bandit is. Um and then this is
the reward of the action that's actually
taken.
There's a variety of simple strategies
for exploration uh and including some
that you can show that are are optimal.
Um and you can often kind of analyze
algorithms and provide theoretical
guarantees on regret. Uh the
um and then also even the algorithms
that like you can kind of theoretically
make some guarantees about in practice
um performance can vary. Uh and so to
get a little bit more intuition actually
no before we do that we're going to play
a game in a minute but before we do that
let's talk about different strategies
for exploration.
uh so
the specifically in in bandits uh so not
in MDPs
so one approach is when you're selecting
different restaurants for example uh if
you haven't explored a restaurant then
you could choose to be optimistic about
that restaurant uh and that will
incentivize you to explore new
restaurants rather than always being
greedy with respect to restaurants
you've tried before
and so the way this could work is you
could track the average reward that you
have received in the past for each of
the actions.
And then if you were to exploit, you
would just take the action that has the
maximum average reward for the things
that you've seen so far. Uh but instead,
if we want to actually encourage the
algorithm to visit new things, then we
could um we still want to visit uh
actions that we think have high average
rewards. so that if we go to a
restaurant that's really bad, we maybe
don't go to it again. But we're going to
add a term that is some kind of variance
of our reward estimate. Uh this is
basically like if this variance is high,
that means that we're uncertain about
the reward for that action.
And if we're uncertain, then we're going
to basically give this sort of bonus,
this sort of reward bonus um on top of
our estimate of the average reward to
encourage our algorithm to explore
things that are uncertain or things that
have high variance.
And so the intuition here is that we're
assuming that unknown things are going
to be good until we actually then
observe them. And if we then observe
them and they're really bad, then um
then we'll act accordingly in the
future. the variance will go down and
the reward estimate will go down and
this is a way to kind of balance
exploration and exploitation. Yeah. So
the question is how would you choose in
this case an action that you haven't
seen before. So if you haven't seen an
action before then your variance
estimate will probably will be something
like infinite for example. Uh and then
the um and then this will encourage it
to explore basically all of the actions
that it hasn't explored first at least
once. Um and then from there your
variance will go your variance estimate
um or your uncertainty about an action
will go down over time. Uh and and yeah
so this is basically if you haven't done
anything before it will incentivize it
to um to visit that first.
Cool. So this is a a popular algorithm.
You can actually kind of derive
guarantees for it. Um it's called upper
confidence bound or one version of it is
called upper confidence bound. Um
there's another approach that you can
also take uh that
um is actually harder to show guarantees
for but can work pretty well in
practice. Uh and we actually saw
something like this uh in the last
lecture. Uh and essentially what you're
trying to do is you're trying to
estimate uh the probability of getting
good rewards from each of the arms of
the bandit.
Uh and so the way this would work is you
assume that there's sort some sort of
kind of distribution of re rewards uh
for each of the actions.
And this defines kind of a partially
observed MDP where you don't know the
parameters of the reward function. You
don't know if you're going to get a good
reward or bad reward. And so you'll then
actually try to model and form an
estimate of the likelihood of getting
rewards. by trying to model these
parameters and your uncertainty over it.
Uh so you'll form an estimate with any
data that you've seen so far. Then
you'll actually sample um an MDP from
your model of possible MDPs of the
world. And then you'll take the optimal
action assuming that your sample was
correct
and then repeat that process to update
your kind of beliefs again and uh then
sample a new MVP and repeat the process.
Um, and we'll kind of walk through an
example, but the intuition here is that
you can kind of iteratively improve your
model of the bandit and act according to
one of the models that is covered by u
one of the potential uh kind of sets of
probabilities uh that's modeled by your
uh your MDP model. One last note, um
these are actually methods that are
widely used and studied in industry for
recommenders and ad placement. Uh the
everything we've been talking about so
far is for these sorts of like small
bandit problems, but they are actually
quite relevant uh for a number of
practical problems even when you don't
have like uh longer episodes or episodes
with state. Um and now let's play like a
little game to get some intuition for
how this works. So uh here is
um a little simulation. um say that you
are hired as the head of drug
development uh at a prestigious research
hospital. Uh things are going well um
and now uh there's kind of some sort of
plague and you need to figure out what
drugs are going to be effective for
addressing the plague and you want to
save people's lives um by giving them
the drug that's most effective.
Now, um you can recognize this as a
bandit problem where each drug you don't
know how capable it's going to be. And
we can say that maybe there's maybe
there's somewhere around 5,000 patients
uh and there's maybe around 10 different
drugs that you're considering. Uh, and
your goal is to try to understand well
try to save lives, try to save as many
cumulative lives as possible um as uh
but also balancing um kind of saving
lives right now versus saving lives in
the future as you learn information
about each of the drugs.
Cool. Um so let's play uh who wants to
suggest a drug? Drug one. Okay. So we
see that uh we prescribed drug one, the
patient lived. Uh so that's good. Uh who
wants to pick a drug? Yeah. Four. Okay.
We also see the patient live. This is
good. On a good track. Yeah.
>> 10
died. Okay. Yeah.
>> Seven
lived. Okay. So 1, four, and seven are
looking better than 10 right now.
Someone else.
Yeah. Six. Still exploring. Patient
died.
>> Five.
Died. Okay. Not so good.
Who else? Yeah.
>> Seven. Okay. Maybe we want to start
exporting. Patient lived again. So that
seems like pretty good. Who wants to
suggest? Yep. Two. Patient died.
Not so good.
Yeah. Seven. Okay.
Patient lived again. Pretty good.
What do we want to do next?
Seven. Okay. Do we want to keep doing
seven? Patient died.
Yeah. Eight. Patient died.
Seven. Patient lived. All right. Should
we just keep on going seven at this
point? Are we happy with seven? Try
nine. Patient live.
Try one.
>> Try one. Patient died.
>> Four. Patient lived.
Four again. Patient died.
Nine. Patient lived.
Three. Patient died.
Nine. Patient lives.
Okay, we like nine.
Cool. Maybe let's keep on doing nine.
>> Patient is living a lot. Great. Um,
okay. We have one patient's eye. So,
let's say that we kind of kept on going
with nine for a while. Um,
and then we can plot actually well with
5,000. Wish I could just say like keep
on doing nine. Uh, maybe we'll stop
there. We can actually plot the regret.
So, um, this was the true efficacy of
the drug. Uh and we can see that nine
actually was the best one. So we
actually found the best one which is
good. Um seven was also pretty good. Uh
and then we can also plot the number of
lives that are saved by different
algorithms. And so higher here is
better. Uh and we see that the posterior
sampling approach and in this case what
posterior sampling would be doing is
modeling the probability of the efficacy
of each drug and then based on his
estimate of that picking um something
that's uh that is better. Uh and we can
see that how well we did right here is
in purple. It's a little bit hard to
tell just because it's a little small,
but we can see that generally like looks
like we're doing pretty well uh relative
to the algorithms. Um and then you can
also plot regret over time. Uh and
actually here we can see that we're
actually doing better than all the
algorithms. So you guys are pretty good.
Nice. Um maybe there's some luck
involved there. So this is just a single
run. Uh and what these different
algorithms are is you see greedy is
showing green. uh greedy is just picking
the best thing you've seen so far. Uh
and you over time, especially with more
and more trials that you might be
running, like more and more patients,
more and more ad placements, whatever,
um it's getting a lot worse. Uh in this
case, we saw that posterior sampling,
yellow is like by far the best
algorithm. Um and then the other
algorithms, uh red is showing epsilon
greedy. Uh blue is showing UCB. So
that's the first algorithm we talked
about with being optimistic about
uncertain actions. Um, so this is
basically showing that kind of the
trade-off between different algorithms.
Um, one other thing to note that epsilon
greedy, it's a bit more greedy. And so
we see that with when you have fewer
patients, it actually is doing better
than UCB, but then in the long run, UCB
is doing better because it's actually,
um, optimizing a bit more for making
sure that you're exploring more actions
and so in the long run, um, it's able to
take more optimal actions in the future.
Um, is there a mathematical reason why
posterior sampling does better? um than
than UCB and epsilon greedy. Yeah. So
the I don't want to go too much into the
math and actually posterior sampling um
for this MDP you probably could analyze
it. Uh and um but in general it's
actually pretty it can be hard to derive
like general theoretical guarantees for
it. Um with regard to epsilon greedy the
um it uh the I guess it come some of it
comes down to that that value of epsilon
um and like tuning it uh to be and
generally with epsilon greedy uh you'll
often choose epsilon to be like smaller
and smaller over time um and that that
like that hyperparameter would probably
like drastically impact performance
because at this point in training um if
epsilon is constant you're going to be
keeping on uh you're going to be still
occasionally taking random drugs and at
that point you already know a lot about
the drug and prescribing a random drug
is a very poor choice.
Okay. Um cool. So if you also if you
want to play more you can um I'll put
the the website in the slides. Okay. So
that's exploration and bandits.
Now what does this look like for
robotics language models and larger
MDPs?
Different people have different opinions
on this. uh I have a somewhat uh
pessimistic opinion on it. Uh and in
particular, there's actually a lot of
research that try to translate these
ideas to larger MDPs. Uh for example, um
you can try to formulate some estimate
of uh whether you've taken an action or
not and give reward bonuses for novelty
for visiting new states, for taking new
actions. uh and similarly uh like
posterior sampling you can try to like
figure out uh kind of models of
different dynamics and so forth uh and
act accordingly uh but at the end of the
day when you're in a very large MDP uh
exploration from scratch is generally
intractable uh so for example if you
randomly initialize a transformer
language model uh and try to figure out
how to make a user happy uh or some
other reward function like like up votes
or anything like that. Um, actually like
just using up votes to train a language
model from scratch uh isn't going to
work. There's just like the sheer
vastness of the possible space of tokens
is way too large uh at least relative to
um the patients that uh most users will
have. Likewise in robotics, if you're
trying to even just learn how to like I
I don't know kind of pour water from
from one cup to another cup, um you're
going to be stuck in a realm where
you're just kind of randomly moving arms
around uh rather than actually doing
things that are useful uh if you're
starting completely from scratch.
uh instead um generally what exploration
looks like uh in these larger domains is
to rely heavily on demonstrations uh or
on base models that were pre-trained on
on data and demonstrations. So for
example uh reinforcement learning has
been quite successful in language models
because uh and particularly in scenarios
where you have a strong base model that
already knows how to write coherent
sentences and already knows uh kind of
roughly how to approach certain kinds of
prompts or certain kinds of problems. Uh
and likewise uh in uh in robotics if you
have demonstrations of example behavior
that achieve high reward then um then
start using that as a starting point for
reinforcement learning is very powerful.
Um and generally these models are like
they they're providing an initialization
that's really excellent for exploration
and seeking out potential uh potential
things. Uh wherever feasible it's also
quite useful to use shaped rewards u
because that can guide any sort of
exploration process as well. Uh, and
this could be um if you're in
simulations, you can handcode sparse uh
like dense rewards or um if you're
learning like singlestep rewards from
preferences that actually also provides
a fairly dense reward signal.
This isn't to say you could also kind of
combine some of these ideas with
demonstrations and base models. Um but
generally you get a lot further um from
from starting with this kind of
initialization.
Okay, that said, um there is still like
potentially an exploration problem that
we started to talk about last time and I
want to revisit that uh now that we've
actually started to learn about um
exploration in uh in kind of standard
MDPs.
Yeah, exactly. So the idea here is that
if you're um in these kinds of MDPs,
this state space is enormous uh and all
of the like possible actions you can
take is enormous as well. And these this
is a way to bias the model towards a
part of the state space that is um that
is going to get high reward. Yeah.
Giving it bias of like these are the
kinds of things I want you to do. Okay.
So um in particular what I'd like to
talk about is like say you have some
model that that has been trained and it
can do a variety of things but um
there's scenarios where when you're
actually deploying that policy uh you
actually even if you have a lot of prior
experience you might need to explore at
test time uh because you might not have
all the information you need to get high
reward. And so we we talked about a
couple examples on Wednesday where for
example you might need to find
ingredients in a kitchen. And to do that
you can't just like start cooking. You
need to open drawers, open cabinets and
so forth to try to seek out uh
information. Uh and second um in
language models for reasoning you might
need to explore different strategies
that might lead to uh a solution to a
problem um rather than simply trying to
start like writing tokens that you think
uh might lead to the solution.
Now we talked about this kind of meta
problem where we're optimizing a policy
with history or with memory. Uh and
generally memory should allow agents to
be able to explore and exploit uh
because they're able to kind of try
different actions and remember what they
did and then use that information about
where ingredients are to then solve the
problem. But we talked about how if we
optimize exploration and exploitation
together with an endto-end objective, uh
this is hard because we have this
chicken and egg problem where if we
haven't yet learned how to explore, then
we can't actually get high rewards
because we haven't found the
ingredients. And likewise, if we don't
yet know how to solve the task, then we
get uh low reward for any sort of
exploration behavior.
Um, so there's this coupling problem
[snorts] and we also talked about some
alternative exploration strategies that
are easier to optimize but can lead to
suboptimal performance.
Um, and the
what I'd like to talk about is actually
a method that can both get optimal
exploration and exploitation trade-off
and also be efficient to train. Uh, so
it sort of gets the best of both worlds.
And the idea for this is actually going
to build upon this last alternative
exploration strategy.
Let's write this right here.
So
um the idea here is that you can try to
for different environments or different
tasks you could try to fit a dynamics
model in a reward model and then try to
explore in ways that uh tell us more
information about our model of the
environment.
uh and this should incentivize the the
uh the agent or the policy to actually
seek out additional information to
explore in a way that's decoupled from
uh executing
uh on executing on the task.
Uh and so um and if you do this and you
have different MDPs that are uh
correspond to like navigating to
different circles uh and then you try to
incentivize it to take trajectories that
lead to a better model of reward and
better model of dynamics, you'll
actually get uh a trajectory that looks
something like the purple trajectory
where it's explicitly trying to visit
states that allow it to learn where the
reward function is going to be.
Um now, uh this can learn efficient
exploration strategies, but it it has
its downsides and it can be suboptimal
in some scenarios. Uh for example, if
there's distractors, like if there's um
like pictures on the wall, for example,
then it's going to be looking at all the
pictures on the wall to learn a good
model of those different environments.
So we can build upon this idea uh and
try to learn how to explore without
learning a model. Uh and um in
particular instead of trying to learn a
dynamics and reward model uh we can
instead try to be able to predict what
the task is. So we're going to label
each task with a identifier mu. Uh this
could be either like a one hot like an
index uh or it could be um a language
description or it could be um kind of
some more continuous uh description of
the task like continuous vector
and
then what we could do is we could try to
explore in a way that allows us to
predict what the task is at hand. Uh so
for example we'll have um our
uh say that we have two policies an
exploration policy and exploitation
policy. Uh in practice you could combine
these uh but uh
it's helpful to think about them as
separate. So we'll have our exploration
strategy. This is our exploration
policy. This is going to produce some
experience in a particular task.
And our goal is for it to be able to
explore to be able to discern different
tasks. And so we could separately train
a model that's going to be predicting
the task identifier from the experience
that we've collected so far.
And if we do something like this, then
this sort of exploration objective is
completely separate from actually
executing on the task. This is the goal
here is to be able to predict the task
identifier.
And then separate from this, we could
train a policy
that's trying to execute on the task
just using the identifier for the task.
Uh and this this is just multitask
learning or multitask reinforcement
learning. And this we can train um just
with uh optimizing reward and it doesn't
rely on having good exploration.
Uh so here we we're able to decouple the
objective for execution. So it doesn't
rely on exploration and have an
exploration objective um just based on
identifying the task that isn't uh
dependent on how well you do the task.
Uh so on the slides we'll train a policy
and a task identification model so that
we collect data that allows for accurate
task prediction and then we'll also
train a policy that's conditioned on the
task um the task ID um in order to um
yeah maximize reward for each task. So
which part of this is the exploration?
Is it the model that predicts the
identifier? So the exploration is really
this policy right here. And this is this
model is actually just going to be used
for the reward for this. And so we're
going to be um the reward for this
policy will be basically how well this
model is at is at identifying the task
or basically the negative error of this
task identifier model. Uh good question.
The question is do is this generaliz
generalize to new unseen task
categories? Uh this can actually
struggle with generalization. uh and
we'll talk about that. Let's go through
meta testing and then we'll we'll talk
about that. So this is how roughly how
training works and then at test time if
you've trained all of these different
things then you can take your
exploration policy run it to collect
experience then feed that experience
into your task identifier model to get a
task ID and then take that task ID and
feed that as input to your execution
policy to then execute uh the task. So
you'll then explore and then uh identify
the task and then exploit.
Um now getting back to that question um
the upside of this is you don't need to
model dynamics or rewards. You're just
like learning this um this model that's
predicting the task identifier. But if
the task identifier is just like a one
hot vector for example, this probably
like isn't going to generalize to new
tasks very well. uh and we'll see a
solution to that on the next slide. Uh
the question is uh what is the main
difference from blackbox metarl that we
talked about before? Um we so we are
still sampling different MDPs. Uh the
main difference is simply the objective
for uh the exploration part. Uh so and
well I guess there's two main
differences. one is the that the
objective for the exploration part and
then the second is that um here we're
going to be maximizing rewards similar
to blackbox metaarl um but we're
actually going to be giving it this task
identifier so that it doesn't need to
rely on exploration uh or a good
exploration strategy when trying to
learn how to do the task.
Now we have this generalization problem
uh and we actually also have a way to
address this. So instead of using this
task identifier directly, we can
actually try to learn a more compressed
representation of the task uh that will
generalize more effectively than like a
one hot vector. So as an example, um
when we learn the execution policy,
we're also going to identify information
that's needed for solving the task. And
so say that our identifier consists of a
few things that are relevant and a few
things that are not relevant. Uh, so it
contains things like wall color and
decorations, but then it also contains
information about where the ingredients
are.
Then we'd like to use and similar if you
had a one hot vector would also contain
information that might be irrelevant
because you might have two kitchens that
have ingredients in the same place but
then have other things that are
spurious. And we'll try to then
bottleneck this representation to
compress away the stuff that's not
needed for solving the task.
And if we can do this then this sort of
representation should generalize better.
And then when we learn to explore
instead of learning to explore to to to
be able to predict the identifier here
we'll learn to explore so that we can uh
recover this compressed task
representation. Um and so try to be able
to um explore so that you're able to
predict um what this Z representation
for the task is.
Now how do you actually compress uh
representations in neural networks? So
before we go into the details of this
algorithm, let's talk about that a
little bit.
So um we have
we have our task identifier
mu mui uh and then we'd like to
have a neural network that uses that to
uh predict zi
and then we'll then have a policy that
takes this and the state uh and outputs
the action.
And if we train this whole thing uh end
to end uh it may not like it it's not
necessarily incentivized to actually
compress information here uh to actually
remove uh information about decorations
for example.
Uh so one thing we could do is we could
simply add noise to this representation.
Um and so if you take this uh and
instead of feeding it directly um here
you could take this output zi and then
right here you could basically add some
noise. So this would right here what
you're doing is you're adding some noise
where the noise is kind of sampled from
a gausian distribution. And if you add
noise then this is going to discard
information uh because you're adding uh
you're kind of corrupting the signal
uh but you might discard some good
information
uh especially if you do this only at
test time. Now in principle you could
also train with this noise to encourage
it to discard information from Z.
But if you train the policy with this
noise as input, then what it could just
do is it could just increase the
magnitude of ZI here so that the
magnitude of the noise is a lot smaller
in comparison.
And so if you just add noise, the model
can compensate and still pass in a lot
of information uh through this task
representation.
So that's not a great solution,
but um what we can do is we can just
also prevent the model from increasing
the magnitude. Uh we can just add a loss
that uh we can kind of modify our
training loss for the policy to include
a term that's going to minimize the
magnitude of Z.
And if you do this, you're kind of then
um now if it kind of blows up the
magnitude of Z, then it um it will have
a high loss here. And so it'll be forced
to keep that magnitude down to be lower.
Um so that it is actually forced to com
to uh remove information that isn't
needed. And any sort of magnitude it
does introduce uh will it will be
incentivized to only have information
that's needed for predicting the action.
Um, this is called an a variational
information bottleneck. Uh, which is
kind of a fancy term for saying that
you're adding noise and then also
modifying your loss term to have this L2
penalty on your representation.
One of the reasons why this is called a
variational information bottleneck is
that um this objective is actually
equivalent to uh minimizing the kale
divergence between your uh uh if you
think about this as a distribution um
because this is now kind of a gausian
distribution with a mean at zi and a
variance according to um to the variance
of epsilon uh that's equivalent to
minimizing the kale divergence between
that distribution and uh the unit
gausian distribution.
Yeah. So the question is why are we
creating a representation of a one hot
vector. So if we go back to the
algorithm we talked about before where
we are exploring to generate experience
then trying to identify the task and
then condition it on that task. the if
we then want to quickly solve a new task
then um we'll be able to use our policy
to explore but then after we explore if
our representation is a one hot vector
here if it's a new task then that new
task may not cleanly fit within one of
the previous one hot vectors and so we'd
like to have a more continuous space
that's more compactly representing the
the task uh and essentially learn like a
this latent task representation
that will generalize to new tasks. Yeah.
So the question is don't we need more
information about the task like whether
or not two tasks are related to each
other? Um now I guess
the so when you think about a oneh hot
um it doesn't really seem like it is
necessarily capturing that much
information but a one hot vector
actually cap is um is actually less
compressed than um something that is uh
that is um
something that's like a more continuous
or or less uh discrete representation.
So say for example um let's see let's
say say for example that one of your
tasks is like to go here. This is like
task one. Uh task two is to go here. Uh
task three is to go here and task like
four is to go here. Then task one and
task four are very similar. uh but when
you use one hot vectors uh to represent
them uh they they are not uh they're
kind of represented completely
separately. Uh and if you try to um
learn a task representation that's
compressing these then it will actually
learn a representation that puts these
much closer to each other. Uh the
question is do you need to add epsilon
to the loss? So the it doesn't end up
coming into the loss. Uh but you do need
to add it when you're actually training
the neural network. So you're adding the
the noise and you sample the noise every
like resample the noise every single
time. Um and the epsilon is sampled from
this distribution and you can sort of
think about this distribution as coming
into uh the the loss. Um but you don't
need to add epsilon to anywhere into the
loss. uh it just comes out to this.
Okay. So let's let's like walk through
actually like what this algorithm looks
like more completely.
So
you
um first let's talk about just like
executing on the task separate from
exploration. Uh so our goal is to learn
this task representation, this latent
task representation and how to solve the
task. And to do this, we're going to
have uh we have our task identifier and
we're going to have a network that uh
that produces zi. We're going to
uh add noise to get zi plus epsilon. Uh,
and then the um and then we're going to
pass this and the state into our this is
our execution policy that's going to
produce
an action.
And
we can think about this as having two
parts. So we have the execution policy
right here that takes as input um the
noisy ZI and the state to produce the
action. And then we also have this part
right here. Uh and we'll uh write this
as a some encoder f that maps from uh
mui to zi.
uh the we can write this as a
distribution uh because if you kind of
fold this noise into a distribution like
this this will be um some distribution
that is uh let's call this now call this
zbar this is a distribution that is a
gausian with mean of um of zbar i and
the and some variance
Let's just write it as variance like
that.
Um, so we have these are the two things
that have parameters f and pi. And we're
going to train both of these neural
networks to maximize reward so that
we're actually learning a representation
such that we can solve the task and
predict actions that maximize reward.
Uh, and then we're also going to add the
regularization on uh on Z. And so uh our
objective here will be maximizing the
sum of expected rewards under our
execution policy.
Uh and since we're maximizing here,
we're also going to be uh minimizing uh
this term right here, which is the
equivalent to the KL divergence. So
we'll be maximizing the negative kl
divergence between
f of zi given
mui
and this uh
unit gausion.
So on the slides um there's the
objective and this is just trying to
solve the task and also learn a latent
task representation. based off of the
task ID. It's going to be a vector. So Z
is going to be a vector. Um and so this
should be an I. Uh the yeah, it'll be a
vector. Um and
you Yeah. Yeah. So the question is why
are we adding um this information
bottleneck or this kale divergence? Uh
the reason is that we want to learn like
a a nice task representation that's
throwing away information. And if we
don't add that term, then this Z right
here, this representation of the task uh
might still contain a lot of information
that are irrelevant uh for actually
solving the task. Uh and so it might
contain um like if for example you have
uh two tasks that have the ingredients
in the same exact place, but something
has changed about the environment like
the the wall color is different or
different objects are in different
places, but those are irrelevant to
solving the task. then Z will include
those things that are irrelevant and
then when you go to explore you're then
going to be exploring things that are
irrelevant to the task. Yeah. So the
question is um we are given the task ID
during training. Uh we actually don't
need it at test time. Um so what does
this look like to generalize to new
tasks? uh when you are faced with a new
task, you're going to use your
exploration policy to explore and then
predict a um instead of predicting UI,
you're actually going to be predicting
ZI, your latent task representation, and
then feeding that into your execution
policy uh to then like execute or
exploit on the task. The question is,
can you train the execution policy to
attend to the relevant parts? So if you
have a really good task representation
um that doesn't have irrelevant uh
irrelevant parts of the t like
irrelevant things in it then you can
skip this step um and basically like
zero out those parts of the task
representation. Uh this would be in
scenarios where you don't have a one dot
vector but you already know like um like
maybe one task uh maybe if you have like
language strings for example and one
task is turn left uh one task is turn
right um another task maybe is the same
as turn left. It's like and you have the
task string for it. It's basically the
same exact task. Another task is to like
move forward. Uh if these are your
different tasks, you you can get away
with like this is probably already a
very compact representation because it's
telling you like are you turning, are
you moving? Um and so it's already
telling you about the relationship
between different tasks. And so if if
your task representation is telling you
about those relationships, then um or
for example, if you had a task
representation that's like um the
coordinates of where you're trying to
go, then you're going to have a task ID
that's very similar between these two
tasks and that will already be quite
compressed. Um in those cases, you can
skip this step uh because those
representations will already um exclude
irrelevant information. Uh but then if
you instead have a task ID that's that's
one hot or that isn't very informative
then you need to uh compress that out
the and otherwise there isn't like this
is the one of the better mathematical
frameworks for encouraging it to attend
to like the relevant parts. Yeah.
Um I guess in principle if you had a way
to like change the way that this is
making decisions based on UI you might
also be able to do that. Yeah. So what's
the advantage of outputting a
distribution? So the the distribution
here is what allows us to compress uh
and so by adding noise or um by making
this a stochastic neural network the um
we're able to remove information from
it. Whereas if you are outputting like
if you're passing a continuous vector
through uh the
um there are kind of huristic ways to
try to compress for example like by
compressing the dimensionality uh but
you can still pass uh like infinite
information through even like a
one-dimensional continuous variable. Uh
and so this is one way that can um that
can uh like even in theory reduce
information.
So now let's talk about exploration. So
our goal in exploration is to be able to
try to predict Z and the um
we will I don't know what notation I
used. Um so our goal is to try to be
able to collect uh data that's
predictive of um of Z. Uh in practice,
by the way, you can train both of these
policies at the same time.
Um,
and we need to think about how we would
formulate a reward function that uh
encourages it to be predictive um of Z.
The
I don't know if I'll just pick some
notation. So say that we have um we're
going to be learning some model
uh that's trying to be able to predict Z
from the data that we've collected. And
if we have some exploration policy
that's been exploring,
then we need to figure out how uh how to
reward it uh accordingly. And one thing
that you could do is you could collect
some data and then at the end of a
trajectory, for example, see how well
you can predict Z and then have the
reward be the negative prediction error
for Z and then zero everywhere else. Uh
but if we did that, we'd have a very
sparse reward. uh we'd only have it at
the end of the trajectory. And what we
can do is we could actually like
incrementally at each time step look at
how much information we're gaining about
Z. Uh and that's going to give us a more
dense reward. And so specifically uh the
when we're trying to train our
exploration policy uh pi exploration the
you can think about um the reward
for sat.
Um we could have it be the negative
uh prediction error
at
time step t. Um, and that would be
something that's like fairly
reasonable. Uh, but the action like this
particular time step, um, we're only at
this time step, we're actually gaining
just like one time step worth of
information. And if we wanted to
quantify that information, we could
actually look at what was our prediction
error at the previous time step and look
at the relative like difference in the
error at the previous time step versus
the error at the current time step. And
that's how much information we gained uh
from taking this action.
And so we could define the reward to be
the prediction error
at t minus one
minus the prediction error at time t.
And so how much like how and this is
something that will should be decreasing
over time. uh and this is basically how
much uh how better are we at predicting
zi at the current time step relative to
the previous time step. Uh where
prediction error is something like uh
is like z hat minus uh the true
zi.
And so we're training this model. Uh we
want this to be kind of per step
information gain. And so if we look at
all of the states up until the current
time step, uh
versus all the time steps up to the
previous time step, um we can measure
this notion of information gain.
I guess maybe also to make this a little
bit more clear, if this is prediction
error at time t, then this means that um
z hat is the estimate from
uh predicting z
from the data up until
time t. So everything in the trajectory
up until time t.
Cool. Um so this has like like many
research algorithms this has a somewhat
mangled forced acronym. Um so decoupled
reward free exploration and execution in
meta or dream. Um and you'll be
implementing uh this algorithm in
homework 4.
So
um we talked before about how if you
train end to end uh like if you train
meta RL methods end to end and you're
trying to optimize for both exploration
and execution you have this coupling
problem and um the the benefit is that
you can get optimal exploration and the
downside is that uh you're very very
inefficient and you can show that this
algorithm um under fairly mild
assumptions will actually recover ever
optimal exploration and exploitation. Uh
um and then if you look at the
efficiency which is where endto-end
optimization struggled uh you can think
about it you can construct a simple
bandit problem where a bandit like
problem where you have these different
arms
and arm zero instead of being a typical
action is going to tell you what is the
optimal action.
And so if you for example learn the
strategy of taking action zero and then
taking the optimal action then that's
like optimally exploring and then
exploiting
and an end toend optimization you can
actually like quantify how many samples
it needs for the metalarning process.
you get something like a^ squ log a
where a is the number of arms or the
number of actions whereas the dream
algorithm requires only a log a there's
some assumptions here in terms of like
using keyarning uh using um uniform
exploration in the um in kind of the
outer loop of the algorithm and you can
look at basically the kind of the
efficiency um like how um how efficient
is the algorithm you can see that uh
dream is able to get um is able to kind
reached the optimal behavior in many
many fewer samples than if you to use
end to-end optimization which is shown
in orange as a function of the number of
arms. And so as the problem gets more
and more complicated uh you
um kind of dream is able to do kind of
far far better than endtoend
optimization.
Um we can also kind of empirically look
at things. So, here's an example of a
meta RL problem where different tasks
correspond to going to different um
objects with different colors and the
color of the object is written on the
wall. Uh and so and the agent starts
over here and it needs to walk around
the wall, walk around the wall, read the
um read the color and then go to the
correct object. So, it's exploring and
then or seeking information and then uh
exploiting gets pixel rewards. And if
you compare end-to-end algorithms that
are shown here, um they really really
struggle to do this sort of end to end
like learning to explore problem. Uh if
you use one of the alternative
strategies that we talked about on
Wednesday, uh you can do better in
theory, but um it's you still have a
sub-optimal exploration strategy.
Whereas with this algorithm, you're able
to actually uh learn how to explore fi
like go find the sign and then go to the
correct object um by actually by trying
to uh kind of decouple exploration for
identifying the task and exploitation of
solving the task.
Cool. Um and then you can actually see
this. So, here's a a video of the
exploration episode where it's walking
around um and going to read the sign on
the wall in this simple environment and
then after it reads the sign um it's
able to go to the the blue key.
Yeah, that's a great question. So, this
is um the question is like this is a
setting where like exploration and
exploitation you can kind of first
explore and then exploit. You might also
have tasks where you need to interle
exploration and exploitation where you
first need to like find some information
then use that to like accomplish a
subtask and then find some exploration
again. Um we have done some work that
tries to combine them and you can for
example create a single policy that uses
the reward to identify the task combined
with the task reward. Um and if you're
interested I can kind of point you to a
relevant work there.
Okay. Um so to summarize um learning to
explore and learning policies that know
how to explore uh end to end um can
learn optimal exploration and
exploitation. Uh but if exploration is
hard it's pretty hard to optimize and we
saw an example of that where all of the
the methods were kind of flatlining and
not learning good exploration. Um
alternative strategies are easier to
optimize and um can be principled but
can also be suboptimal by large amounts
and be very inefficient about
exploration. Um and this decoupled
approach leads to the optimal strategy
um is also easy to optimize. So it sort
of gets the kind of the best of both
worlds. Uh it does require this this
task identifier. You need to at least be
able to enumerate your tasks and know
which of those tasks you're in. Um and
that's kind of the the key thing that
it's using in order to get the benefits.
Cool. Um we have a little bit of time
and so you can actually um I want to
briefly talk about one application. So
you can take this algorithm and uh use
it in a domain that's a little bit
different from what we've seen before.
And this domain is trying to find bugs
uh in different computer programs. uh
and in particular uh in intromputer
science courses although this could
probably apply to other programs as well
um it's really cool for students to be
able to like make computer programs uh
it's like very rewarding for them to
like write a program as they're learning
how to code uh then that creates like a
a program like this so on code.org or uh
students code up this game called bounce
that looks a bit like pong or one side
of pong uh where the goal is to hit a
ball into the goal. Um in CS 106A at
Stanford uh students code up breakout uh
and so uh they might code up a program
like this. Uh this is an example of a
buggy game where um where the the the
ball actually kind of gets kind of sort
of skewered by the paddle. It kind of
bounces off the paddle rather than going
and and losing a point or losing a life.
uh and we can basically treat different
student programs as different tasks
where our goal is to explore and find
the bugs that might exist and our
ultimate goal is to then be able to
provide feedback to the student on the
different bugs in their program.
One of the other things about this is
it's really timeconuming for TAs or
instructors to actually grade and give
feedback on these assignments because
you often end up playing the game in
order to figure out and find the bugs.
Um cool. So we can use meta RL. We can
actually use exactly the dream algorithm
um and train it to be able to identify
um uh different uh different kind of
distinguishing factors from different
students. Um and it can learn
exploration strategies like um what
happens if the ball hits the goal. So
here it's trying to actually play the
game successfully. It can also check and
act so that like what happens if the
ball hits the floor. So it's actually
purposely trying to like not hit the
ball. Um or also try to hit the wall
instead of the goal. I mean, this is an
example of a buggy program that creates
lots of different balls um as soon as
the ball hits the the wall.
Uh and then there was an experiment in
106A uh two years ago in the spring 2023
quarter uh where TAS actually used the
meta RL algorithm and the policy to
basically grade and pre-populate the
rubric for grading. Um, and then they
they kind of just verified that the
rubric answers were correct from
watching the videos of the Meta RL agent
playing the game. Uh, and it led to 44%
faster grading and also 6% more accurate
grading. Um, and the TAs generally liked
using it. Uh, they also used it in at
least one subsequent quarter um, because
they they liked using it so much.